Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is פ"א, Pei Aleph,
סנהדרין Sanhedrin 81, we pick up on the משנה mishna and we
are continuing with the issue about חייבי מיתות chayavei misos and so
to speak special cases relating to them. So the משנה mishna says
as follows, מי שנתחייב שתי מיתות בית דין, Mi shenischayev shtei misos
Beis Din, if somebody has done two sins that you're חייב chayav
for two separate executions of the four that we've been discussing, נידונין
בחמורה, nidonin b'chamura, he is given the more weighty punishment, which sort
of is pretty obvious, why should the fact that he's also liable
for a lighter one get him out? We'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. עבר עבירה שנתחייב שתי מיתות, Avar avera shenischayev shtei
misos, נידון בחמורה. nidon b'chamura.
Now, if רבי יוסי אומר נידון בזיקה ראשונה שבאה לו. Rabbi Yosi
omer nidon b'zika rishona sheba lo. Now this sounds like the same
case, but here we're talking about not two separate sins but one
particular עבירה avera that has in it two transgressions, both of which
you're deserving of the death penalty. The גמרא Gemara will talk about
a case, for example, a person having sex with his mother who
is also a married woman, so it's the prohibition of adultery and
the prohibition of a mother and her daughter.
So which one of those does he get? So רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi says, נידון בזיקה, nidon b'zika, excuse me, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma first says נידון בחמורה nidon b'chamura again, so fine, he's just
like the first case, he's חייב chayav two separate מיתות בית דין
misos Beis Din and you get the strict, you execute him with
the more stringent one. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says no, it's
defined by the first זיקה zika like relationship that he had to
this woman and we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara which
if those statuses came at different stages, then he is defined, his
עבירה avera with this woman is defined as the first status that
applied to her. So we'll see about that. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. פשיטא, Pshita, this is obvious that of course
you get the stronger the heavy punishment of the heavy the most
stringent execution. אתגורי איתגר, Itgri itgar, do we think he would be
rewarded for having done two עבירות averos that now we're only going
to give him the lighter one? So אמר רבא הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון שעבר עבירה קלה ונגמר דינו על עבירה קלה.
Amar Rava hacha b'mai askinan kegon she'avar avera kala v'nigmar
dino al avera kala. No, the question is sequence. Somebody did a
sin that you just get the lighter execution for, let's say חנק,
chenek, and then he had גמר דין gmar din and he was
actually that judgment was passed on him, וחזר ועבר עבירה חמורה. v'chazar
v'avar avera chamura. And then after he was already now in you
know in the you know
been judged by בית דין Beis Din and is now חייב chayav
to be executed in this way, he now had the temerity to
do another עבירה, avera, another sin that's deserving of the death penalty
with an even stronger punishment, a weightier form of execution. So the
first one was let's say חנק chenek and the next one was
שריפה. sreifa. Or when he was in prison he killed somebody, so
you know the first one was חנק chenek and then the next
one not prison I know but anyway and then the next one
was
סייף. saif.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
daatach amina, I would have thought to say, כיון דנגמר דינו לעבירה
קלה האי גברא קטילא הוא, keivan d'nigmar dino l'avera kala hai gavra
ktila hu, that once the judgment had already been passed that he's
that he is deserving of execution, this lighter execution חנק, chenek, so
he's already considered like a dead man, dead man walking, and therefore
the other execution isn't even sort of the other judgment isn't even
passed on him. קמ"ל, Kama shma lan, so this teaches us not
that way, that we will hold another court case and pass another
judgment on him. Okay, so at least that gives us a reason
why I might have thought.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says בעי מיניה אבוה דרב יוסף בר חמא
מרבה בר נתן. Ba'ei minei abua deRabbi Yosef bar Chama meRabbah bar
Nasan. מנה הני מילי דאמרי רבנן מי שנתחייב שתי מיתות בית דין
נידון בחמורה. Mina hani milei de'amre rabbanan mi shenischayev shtei misos Beis
Din nidon b'chamura. Okay, how do you know this is true? You
know what רבא Rava said maybe was a good הוה אמינא, havah
amina, if somebody really did a sin and was the judgment was
passed and he already has one judgment of execution against him, maybe
the other one should not take effect on top of that. So
where is this idea that the rabbis teach that if you you're
only judged, you know that you get the weightier one even if
you started with the lighter one? So let's take a look. מי
שנתחייב שתי מיתות נידון בחמורה דכתיב, Mi shenischayev shtei misos nidon b'chamura
dechsiv, because the פסוק pasuk says, והוליד בן פריץ veholid ben paritz
and the person will give birth to a wayward child, שופך דם
shofech dam who is a spiller of blood,
ועשה אחת מאלה ve'asah achas me'eileh and he does one of these
things,
וגם אל ההרים אכל v'gam el he'harim achal and he didn't just
do one of these things but he even ate on the mountains,
ואת אשת רעהו טימא ve'es eshes re'eihu tima and he defiled his
friend's wife, עני ואביון הונה ani v'evyon honah and he oppressed the
poor,
גזלות גזל חבול לא ישיב, gezeilos gazal chavol lo yashiv, he stole,
he didn't return, ואל הגלולים נשא עיניו תועבה עשה v'el hagilulim nasa
einav to'evah asah and he looked towards the abominations towards the idols
and he has done abomination. Okay, so it speaks about somebody doing
a lot of עבירות. averos. So we're going to focus on particular
one. אל ההרים אכל, el he'harim achal, he ate on the mountains,
ואת אשת רעהו טימא, ve'es eshes re'eihu tima, ואל הגלולים נשא עיניו,
v'el hagilulim nasa einav, והוליד בן פריץ, veholid ben paritz, אל הגלולים
נשא עיניו. v'el hagilulim nasa einav. society. So the first thing is
that this person went ahead and was a murderer. He deserves סייף,
sayif, okay, execution by the sword. ואת אשת רעהו טימא, ve-et eshet
re'ehu timme,
and then he defiled his friend's wife, זו אשת איש, zu eshet
ish, בחנק. be-chenek. So that's, you know, that's adultery, that's
חנק. chenek. ואל גילולים נשא עיניו, ve-el gillulim nasa einav, זו עבודה
זרה, zu avodah zarah, which is בסקילה. bi-skilah.
And what does it say at the end? וכתיב, u-chtiv, and then
it says מות יומת דמיו בו, mot yumat damav bo, he will
surely die, his blood is upon him. And we know that phrase
דמיו בו, damav bo, דמיו בו יהיה, damav bo yihyeh, which means
בסקילה. bi-skilah. So here somebody did all these עבירות, aveiros, and he
did lighter ones than סקילה skilah first, and nevertheless he is going
to get the heaviest punishment. All right. מתקיף לה רב פפא בר
יצחק, matkif lah Rav Pappa bar Yitzchak, אימא כולו בסקילה. eima kulu
bi-skilah. I— he says wait a minute, I have a way to
read this verse that all of the עבירות aveiros are talking about
ones that are deserving of סקילה skilah and it doesn't prove your
point at all. How? Let's take a look. והוליד בן פריץ שופך
דם, ve-holid ben paritz shofech dam, a child who is a spiller
of blood, זה בן סורר ומורה, zeh ben sorer u-moreh, that is
the wayward son, which actually works well because it speaks about giving
birth to a בן. ben. And the spiller of blood, even though
he hasn't committed murder, as we said that he's judged על שם
סופו, al shem sofo, so because he will become a murderer, okay,
and that is בסקילה, bi-skilah, it's בסקילה. bi-skilah. ואת אשת רעהו טימא,
ve-et eshet re'ehu timme, זו נערה המאורסה דבסקילה. zu na'arah ha-me'orasah de-bi-skilah.
And about defiling, you know, your friend's wife, an act of adultery,
fine, it could be adultery, but specifically adultery of the נערה המאורסה
na'arah ha-me'orasah which is also בסקילה. bi-skilah. ואל הגילולים נשא עיניו, ve-el
ha-gillulim nasa einav, זו עבודה זרה דבסקילה. zu avodah zarah de-bi-skilah. And
then of course, as you said, abominations is עבודה זרה avodah zarah
which is בסקילה. bi-skilah. So it wouldn't prove anything, they could all
be סקילה. skilah. The Gemara responds, אי הכי, i hachi, מה קמשמע
לן יחזקאל? mai kamashma lan Yechezkel? This is a פסוק pasuk by
יחזקאל. Yechezkel. So what would יחזקאל Yechezkel be teaching us? He just
says you're doing all of these עבירות aveiros and you're חייב סקילה.
chayav skilah. Why say it? It's all obvious. You know, if he's
telling us different עבירות aveiros with different punishments and nevertheless you get
the weightier one, fine, then I understand the point of the פסוק.
pasuk. But what would the point of the פסוק pasuk be according
to you? דילמא, dilma,
so the Gemara says, דילמא תורה קמהדר. dilma Torah ka-mehadder. Maybe he's
just doing חזרה. chazarah. He's repeating the תורה. Torah. He's just teaching
people basic הלכה. halachah. So the Gemara says no, אי הכי, i
hachi, איבעי ליה למהדר כדמהדר משה רבינו. ibei leh le-mehadder ke-di-mehadder Moshe
Rabbeinu. If he's— look, you know, we already have a model for
that, משה, Moshe, משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. You know, he went over
the מצוות. mitzvos. But when he went over the מצוות, mitzvos, he
was very clear what he was talking about and he expanded on
things and he, you know, so why would he sort of do
this in this subtle way if he was just repeating what was
being said earlier and even repeating it in a way that is
less clear than the way it appears in the תורה? Torah? So
it must be he's coming to tell us something else, and therefore
he's coming to tell us the point of our משנה. Mishnah. Okay.
Now that we're looking at this פסוק, pasuk, we're going to have
a different interpretation of it. דרש רב אחא ברבי חנינא, darash Rav
Acha b'rebi Chanina, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, or of a related פסוק,
pasuk, אל ההרים לא אכל. el he-harim lo akhal. This is a
פסוק pasuk about somebody who did not do any of these things.
So the פסוק pasuk here is, this is like a few פסוקים
pesukim before the ones we read. אל ההרים לא אכל, el he-harim
lo akhal, ועיניו לא נשא אל גילולי בית ישראל. ve-einav lo nasa
el gillulei beit Yisrael. He
did not look to the mountains, he did not worship the abominations.
ואת אשת רעהו לא טימא, ve-et eshet re'ehu lo timme, did not
defile his friend's friend, his friend's wife. ואל אשה נדה לא יקרב,
ve-el ishah niddah lo yikrav, and he did not draw close to
a woman who is a נדה. niddah. And then at the end
it says that he is a צדיק, tzaddik, he is a righteous
person and he will surely live. So what are all these various
things? I mean, most of them are clear, but what is— first
of all, let's start with, let's see how the Gemara interprets it.
Okay. אל ההרים לא אכל, el he-harim lo akhal,
he did not eat in the mountains. What does that referring to?
שלא אכל בזכות אבותיו. she-lo akhal bi-zechut avotav. He did not, you
know, eat from the merit of his forefathers. Forefathers are sort of
like the mountains, you know, is often a metaphor for where you
came from, and you are a righteous person in your own and
therefore the rewards that you receive, the divine rewards are due to
your own deeds. You are not doing it, you're not relying on
the merits of your fathers, of your forebears. ועיניו לא נשא אל
גילולי בית ישראל, ve-einav lo nasa el gillulei beit Yisrael, and he
did not go to the abominations. So obviously the Gemara wants to
say, look, if this פסוק pasuk is saying that he's righteous and
he's going to be rewarded and live, it doesn't just mean that
he passively did not do all of these terrible עבירות. aveiros. It
must be talking about something more positive about him. So that's how
we're going to interpret this פסוק. pasuk. So what does that mean?
שלא הלך בקומה זקופה, she-lo halach bi-komah zekufah, that he did not
walk with like a, you know, a very upright posture, sort of
saying like, you know, an arrogant way of being in the world
which is sort of pushing away God's presence. So it's sort of
related to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
But he was humble. Okay. ואת אשת רעהו לא טימא, ve-et eshet
re'ehu lo timme, he did not defile his friend's wife, שלא ירד
לאומנותו של חבירו. she-lo yarad le-ommanuto shel chaveiro. So using it as
a metaphor, you know, don't— he did not encroach on his friend's
livelihood. Wife is often seen as a metaphor for the household, domestic,
a person's, you know, absolute— you know, entire personal life or domestic
life. I guess business is also your professional life, but anyway, that's
what the metaphor here
is. Okay? שלא ירד לאומנותו. she-lo yarad le-ommanuto. חברו chavero ועל אשה
נדה לא קרב ve'al isha nidah lo karav and he did not
draw close to a woman who is a נדה nidah שלא נהנה
מקופה של צדקה shelo ne'ena mikupa shel tzedakah he did not benefit
from the צדקה tzedakah from he didn't take charity even if he
could have, he was poor, he did not want to do that
because that would have felt like it would have sullied him. Again,
this is a little problematic in that it... the associations with נדה
nidah something that is defiling and sullying and so on. Wanted to
be particularly pure.
Obviously you know that is an issue that we need to be
sensitive about, the way in which the פסוקים psukim particularly also פרק
יחזקאל Perek Yechezkel sort of characterize נדה nidah and how that is
not at all helpful for us that are keeping טהרת המשפחה taharat
hamishpacha and also the whole way it's often reframed as טהרת המשפחה.
taharat hamishpacha. Much larger discussion. Anyway,
okay, וכתיב vechtiv and then the end of the פסוק pasuk says
צדיק הוא חיה יחיה. tzadik hu chaya yichye. He is a צדיק,
tzadik, he is righteous, he will live. Okay, so it's not just
he did not do all these terrible things but he did all
of these positive things. כשהיה רבן גמליאל מגיע למקרא הזה keshehaya Rabban
Gamliel magiya lamikra hazeh when Rabban Gamliel came to this verse about
if somebody didn't do all of this, he is a righteous and
he will live, היה בוכה haya bocheh he would cry. ואמר מאן
דעביד לכולהו הוא דחייה ve'amar man de'avid lekulhu hu dechaya if somebody
did has to only if you do all of these? Now again,
all of these not the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, don't
do all these עבירות, aveiros, but somebody has to do all these
good things that we've just now interpreted it, humility and you know
and not eating by the merits of the forebears, not receiving צדקה,
tzedakah, only if you do all of these things will you live?
הוא דחייה? hu dechaya? הוא דחייה? hu dechaya? בחדא מינייהו לא? bechada
mineyhu lo? And just one is not enough? Like it's a very
high standard now the way you're reading the פסוק. pasuk. אמר ליה
רבי עקיבא, amar lei Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva responded, אלא
מעתה ela me'ata no you don't have to read it like that.
You could read it like anyone, not all of them. And I'll
show you. The פסוק pasuk says אל תטמאו בכל אלה al titameu
bechol eleh do not defile yourselves with all of these things. This
is at the end of the whole list of forbidden sexual relationships.
So it says הכא נמי hacha nami you know so בכולהו אין
בחדא מינייהו לא? bekulhu ein bechada mineyhu lo? Is it just saying
you can't do all of these transgressions but one of them would
be okay? No, אלא באחת מכל אלה ela be'achat mikol eleh don't
defile yourself with anyone of these. So here too הכא נמי באחת
מכל אלה. hacha nami be'achat mikol eleh. It says if one person
does even just one of these good traits then he will surely
live. Okay, so that's the end of that פסוק pasuk which was
originally also quoted to show this idea of multiple עבירות aveiros that
are חייב מיתה. chayav mita.
עברה עבירה. avara aveira. Now we're going to deal with this issue
that it was one sin that had two מיתות mitot associated with
it and the תנא קמא Tana Kama says what we would have
assumed, you just give her the more stringent one, but רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi has the interesting position that it's defined based on the
first status that was relevant as this person. So now the גמרא
Gemara will explain. תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. כיצד
אמר רבי יוסי נידון בזיקה
ראשונה? keitzad amar Rabbi Yossi nidon bezika rishona? What does the... what
does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi mean? What is he talking about when
he says the first relation? So here's the scenario. חמותו, chamoto, his
mother-in-law, his wife's mother, who was not married when he married his
wife or was never maybe never married in his lifetime. So his
first relationship to this woman let's call her Sarah, for him Sarah
was never a married woman from the time let's say he became
בר מצוה bar mitzvah she had already maybe she never was married,
her husband had died, she was always a single woman. The first
way she became forbidden to him was when he married Sarah's daughter.
Okay, so חמותו ונעשית אשת איש chamoto vena'asit eshet ish and then
after he married Sarah's daughter Sarah went and got married. So נידון
בחמותו. nidon bechamoto. He's given the status as that of mother-in-law you
know which is אשה ובתה, isha uvita, okay, which is שרפה, sreifa,
that is the punishment and not אשת איש eshet ish which is
חנק. chenek. Anyway חנק chenek is lighter. All right. Okay, so then
it continues and it says נידון בחמותו. nidon bechamoto. Now let's say
it was the reverse, אשת איש ונעשית חמותו. eshet ish vena'asit chamoto.
This woman she was always a married woman Sarah and then he
married her daughter. So first Sarah was forbidden to him as a
married woman and then she became forbidden to him as his wife's
mother. נידון באשת איש. nidon be'eshet ish. So now that's the חידוש.
chiddush. He gets the lighter one, he only gets חנק, chenek, strangulation,
because that was his first way in which the status that was
relevant to him she was already forbidden to him as an אשת
איש. eshet ish. Now what this is a concept of is the
concept of אין איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur,
that if something is already forbidden to you it has a certain
status and then it gains another status which makes it forbidden in
another way, there's the position here which is the position being adopted
by רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that that second status does not take
effect, that you're really are defined your relationship to it is defined
by the first status. Okay but there's some exceptions to that rule
of אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur and
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. So it says
like this: אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא, amar lei Rav
Adda bar Ahava leRava, so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava said to רבא, Rava, חמותו ונעשית אשת איש נידון בחמותו. chamoto
vena'asit eshet ish nidon bechamoto. In the case you said that it
started off as his mother-in-law and then she got married and she
became a married woman and that we would only treat her as
the mother-in-law, one minute, that could be a case of איסור מוסיף,
issur mosif, why?
Let her also be forbidden to him as an אשת איש? eishes
ish? Why? דאמר רבי אבהו מודה רבי יוסי באיסור מוסיף, de-amar Rabbi
Abbahu modeh Rabbi Yosi be-issur mosif,
even though רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi does not hold of this idea
of or holds of the idea of אין איסור חל על איסור,
ein issur chal al issur, one status does not take effect on
top of another one, if the second status is broader then he
would agree. And one way of defining broader here means more people
are forbidden to this thing. So when it was just his mother-in-law,
Sarah was just his mother-in-law and she was single, so then she
was only forbidden to him. Now she gets married. This status of
being a married woman, it's true, she's already forbidden to him, but
she wasn't forbidden to the rest of the world. Now that she's
a married woman, she's forbidden to every man other than her husband.
So the fact that this new status expanded the audience to whom
she is forbidden, that's considered an איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, a new
איסור issur that increases those that it applies to and expands those
it applies to. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi therefore should agree and
therefore should say that she also is forbidden to him as a
married woman. Now you're probably thinking exactly what the response of the
גמרא Gemara is going to be. פא עמוד ב, Pei Alef amud
Beis, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him, אדא
ברי אדא מסיעא בתרי קטלי קטלת ליה? Adda beri Adda masya bitrei
katlei katlat lei?
You want to kill him with two executions? Meaning, yes, fine, she's
also an אשת איש, eishes ish, but that's not relevant, you know,
to him. But that's not relevant because we're talking about a case
that somebody did the sin במזיד be-meizid and he gets the, you
know, the question is how do we execute him? So since already
the first status of mother-in-law we would execute him because of mother-in-law,
we would give him שריפה, sreifah, so then the fact that she
also becomes a married woman, which is חנק, chenek, which is a
lesser punishment, it's not relevant. Yes, sure, fine, she's also a married
woman, big deal. So the question is obviously that was an obvious
answer, what was he thinking? And רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both
say, well no, he meant if he didn't do it intentionally and
it wasn't במזיד be-meizid and it was בשוגג, be-shogeg, so there it
is relevant. But because the second status also takes effect, he would
bring two קרבנות korbanos rather than one. If the second status was
not a broader one, for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi she would only
be defined as the first and therefore if it was בשוגג be-shogeg
it would only be one קרבן. korban. But because now she's also
a married woman and that's a broader one, if he does it
בשוגג be-shogeg he brings two קרבנות. korbanos. But in the context of
intentional, it's irrelevant. He's already getting the stricter punishment. Okay, next משנה,
Mishnah, top of פא עמוד ב. Pei Alef amud Beis. מי שלקה
ושנה בית דין מכניסין אותו לכיפה.
Mi she-lakah ve-shanah Beis
Din machnisin oso la-kippah. This is a famous teaching משנה. Mishnah. Somebody
that got lashes and then did it twice, he repeats the same
עבירה, aveirah, he's a repeat offender. So what would the court do
with him? He is somebody also that does not seem to be
dissuaded by the fact that we give him lashes, so we have
to sort of deal with the social problem here. So the בית
דין Beis Din would put him into a jail, into a כיפה
kippah is like, you know, a dome, some type of an enclosed
built structure, ומאכילין אותו שעורין עד שכריסו מתבקעת, u-ma'achilin oso se'orin ad
she-kreiso misbaka'as,
and you would feed him barley until his stomach would burst. Okay,
now that phrase is interesting. Does it mean it literally? The גמרא,
Gemara, the בבלי Bavli assumes that it means literally, that you would
give him a type of diet, and more about that in the
next משנה, Mishnah, that would actually cause him to die as a
result of that diet. You would indirectly bring about his death, which
is a very harsh way of understanding this. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi more
understands this משנה Mishnah in plus more literally, or actually it is
a little figuratively, it just means you give him as much barley
as he wants, you know, you give him a very meager, like
a very non-fancy diet, but you let him eat his fill. And
it basically is talking about not a way you get the guy
killed, but a type of a prison system. You keep this guy
locked up and you give him meager rations. Okay, very big difference
about how to read the משנה. Mishnah. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says about what this is about. So משום דלקה ושנה בית
דין כונסין אותו לכיפה? Mishum de-lakah ve-shanah Beis Din konsin oso la-kippah?
Just because a guy did something twice you're going to lock him
up and cause him to die or whatever? Like what explanation is
that? Why are we allowed to do this? What's the justification? It's
certainly nowhere in the תורה. Torah. So אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי
שמעון בן לקיש הכא במלקיות של כריתות עסקינן.
Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Lakish hacha be-malkiyos shel krisos askinan. We're not just talking about any
sin that deserves lashes, but specifically a sin that you're you get
כרת kares for. כרת kares is a divine punishment of excision, but
it's a type of a heavenly death. And but if you're given
התראה, hasra'ah, warning, and there are witnesses, they would give you lashes.
But the fact that you were deserving of divine excision gives בית
דין Beis Din the latitude to lock you up and to bring
about your death, as the בבלי Bavli understands
it. So דגברא בר קטלא הוא, de-gavra bar katla hu, this person
is deserving of death because כרת kares is a type of
death,
וקרובי הוא דלא מיקרב. u-karuvi hu de-la mikrav. giving up on his
own soul
I mean literally soul but
life he doesn't care about his life he's acting in a completely
irresponsible way and he's doing these sins that are חייב כרת chayav
kares for so מקריבין ליה את קטליה עילויה makrivin lei es katlei
iluyei so we'll help him out there somebody here that not only
is חייב מיתה chayav misa but doesn't seem to care and welcomes
it upon him all of these sins and so on we'll speed
up that punishment. Okay, that works very much if you understand that
the punishment here is bringing about his death. If you understand this
is more just straight jail, then the justification might more have to
be with sort of societal reasons and we don't need to say
that he's somehow deserving of death. Anyway, but that's how the גמרא
Gemara here understands. אמר ליה רב יעקב לרב ירמיה בר תחליפא תא
אסיברא לך.
amar lei Rav Yaakov leRav Yirmiya
bar Tachlifa ta asibra lach. He said רב יעקב Rav Yaakov said
to רב ירמיה בר תחליפא Rav Yirmiya bar Tachlifa come let me
explain to you במלקות שכרת אחת. bemalkus shekares achas. We're talking about
that somebody did one sin, it yes it is כרת kares for
the reason we said, and he did it multiple times. אבל שתים
ושלש כריתות aval shetayim veshalosh krisos if a person did two or
three things: he ate חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach and he ate
blood and then he ate חלב, chelev, all these things that you
get כרת kares for, so we don't lock him up and throw
away the key. Why? Because איסורי הוא דקא טעים ולא מבטל כוליה
האי. issurei hu deka tayeim velo mevatel kulei hai. He wants to
just taste all these forbidden things, he's trying to satisfy his various
lusts, but it does not show
complete irresponsible behavior. He's not giving up on his life, he's not
surrendering his life to the same degree. He's not saying like I
don't care what happens to me, I'm just going ahead and do
it. He's not really the same type of repeat offender, he's somebody
so that's a different type of behavior and we would handle it
in a different way. Okay, מי שלקה ושנה. mi shelaka veshana. Now
we're going to focus on the fact that we're ready to do
it already after two times. So גמרא Gemara says שנה אף על
גב דלא שילש shana af al gav delo shileish if he did
it twice, even if he didn't do it three times. And this
is the whole question about what establishes a חזקה, hazaka, what establishes
that somebody has a pattern and it's habitual and we can expect
it to happen again. So לימא leima and this is debate of
רבי Rebbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבי
Rebbi says, let's read it: מתניתין דלא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. matnisin
d'lo keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel. It's not like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל האמר עד תלת זימני
לא הויא חזקה. deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel ha amar ad tlas zimni
lo havya hazaka. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
you need three times. This is debate about a woman whose husbands
keep on dying on her, and the גמרא Gemara is concerned that
that might be some causal relationship, and after what stage are you
not allowed, do we say that a man should not marry her?
After two husbands die on her or three husbands? So רבי Rebbi
says after two husbands and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says after three. And the גמרא Gemara says that this is
actually a debate of what establishes a חזקה. hazaka. Some אחרונים acharonim
actually want to say that it's not necessarily, maybe there's two types
of a חזקה. hazaka. There's one where it's habitual and you say
that this is expected behavior, and the other is it's enough to
say it's something we need to be concerned about. There's enough to
be take care about it but not enough to establish that you
definitely can assert habitual behavior. But anyway the גמרא Gemara here frames
this as a debate of רבי Rebbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So let's say it's like רבי Rebbi who
says two times already establishes a חזקה hazaka and not רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. מתניתין דלא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל
דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל האמר
עד תלת זימני לא lo, הויא חזקה. So אמר רבינא amar Ravina,
אפילו תימא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
No, you could say it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. because קסבר
עבירות מחזיקות.
kasavar aveiros
machzikos. It's true he didn't get three lashes, but he did three
sins, or he did the sin three times. He did it once,
got lashes; second time, got lashes; third time he did the sin,
we put him in this כיפה. kipa. So because he now has
established this pattern three times, that's why what we're going to do
to him is not give him lashes but put him in the
כיפה. kipa. Okay, so that makes a lot of sense. So מיתיבי
meisivei גמרא Gemara says I'll challenge you on this. We have a
ברייתא. braisa. עבר עבירה שיש בה מלקות, avar aveira sheyeish bo malkus,
somebody did a sin that has lashes, פעם ראשונה ושנייה מלקין אותו.
paam rishona ushniya malkin oso. The first two times you give him
the lashes. ובשלישית כונסין אותו לכיפה vashlishis konesin oso lakippa is when
you put him into this כיפה. kipa. אבא שאול אומר. Abba Shaul
omer. אבא שאול Abba Shaul says אף בשלישית מלקין אותו. af bashlishis
malkin oso.
No, even on time three
you give him lashes. ברביעית כונסין אותו לכיפה, birviis konesin oso lakippa,
only when he does the sin four times do you put him
into the כיפה. kipa. So this seems, it seems that this debate
is very easily understandable as a debate of is it established after
two or after three, right? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. מאי לאו דכולי עלמא מלקות מחזיקות. mai lav d'chulei alma malkus
machzikos. Is it not the case that what establishes the pattern is
the lashes? Now what does that mean, the lashes establishes the
pattern? The lashes don't mean that he habitual. So what תוספות Tosfos
says is no, what it means is that
we
have established the pattern that lashes do no good to dissuade him
and that he is prepared to sin even though he will get
lashes. So if he's demonstrated that three times, did it once got
lashes, did it twice got lashes, did it three times got lashes
and then did it four times, and then did it the fourth
time, so now we know that for three times he disregarded the
lashes and continued sinning. Okay, that would be the idea that the
lashes establish. So then the גמרא Gemara says if that was the
case we can understand whether you throw him in the כיפה kippa
on time three or on time four. So דכולי עלמא מלקות מחזיקות.
dechulei alma malkus machzikos. The point is the lashes and defying the
lashes is what establishes the pattern. ובפלוגתא דרבי ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל
קמיפלגי, uveflugta deRabbi veRabban Shimon ben Gamliel kamiflegi, and it's the debate
of רבי Rabbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
According to רבי Rabbi two times, so when he did the third
sin he showed now that he twice disregarded the lashes. First sin,
got lashes once. Second sin was regarding the lashes the first time,
got lashes a second time. Then he did the third sin, now
he has disregarded the lashes twice. Okay, and now we'll throw him
into the כיפה. kippa. And for אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, that would
be like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, only when
he did the sin four times because then he would have disregarded
the lashes three times and then we throw him in the כיפה.
kippa. Okay, and so that would make sense. ובפלוגתא דרבי ורבן שמעון
בן גמליאל קמיפלגי. uveflugta deRabbi veRabban Shimon ben Gamliel kamiflegi. But so
you see that they are, that it is the debate of רבי
Rabbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, and that
our משנה Mishnah that says on the third time you throw him
in is רבי. Rabbi. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, no. דכולי
עלמא אית ליה דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. dechulei alma it lei deRabban
Shimon ben Gamliel.
I'm going to continue to insist, says רבינא, Ravina, that everybody holds
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that you go
by three times. Nobody here is holding like רבי Rabbi of two
times. Okay, so what's the debate? והכא בהא קמיפלגי, vehacha beha kamiflegi,
this is the debate. מר סבר עבירות מחזיקות, mar savar aveiros machzikos,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that the third time you throw
him in says that you go by the sins. He sinned three
times and therefore the third time you throw him in. Okay, that's
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and that's also our משנה. Mishnah. ומר סבר,
umar savar, and אבא שאול Abba Shaul holds מלקות מחזיקות. malkus machzikos.
No,
it's not the sinning, it's the defying of the lashes and therefore
you have to wait till the fourth time that he did it,
so then he defied the lashes three times. So everybody could hold
of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. and we don't
have to say that anybody is going like
רבי. Rabbi.
Okay. והדתניא, vehatanya, now the גמרא Gemara says okay fine, I get
that, but now we got another ברייתא Beraisa that we got to
figure out regardless of רבי, Rabbi, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel Okay, here's the ברייתא. Beraisa. התרו בו ושתק התרו בו
והרכין ראשו.
hisru vo veshatak hisru
vo vehirkin rosho. You gave him warnings, let's say you didn't actually
give him lashes, but you knew that he was willful. How much
is the lashes a central part of this? So you said don't
do that עבירה, aveira, don't eat חלב, chelev, and he was silent.
He didn't, it was clear he understood but he didn't say אף
על פי כן. af al pi chen. Okay, he didn't say the
words he needed to say that would allow us to give him
lashes or he nodded his head, והרכין ראשו. vehirkin rosho. פעם ראשונה
ושנייה מתרין בו. pa'am rishona ushniya masrin bo. So the first two
times you give him the warning and you weren't now able to
actually give him the lashes. Okay, שלישית כונסין אותו לכיפה. shlishis konsin
oso lakippa. Third time throw him in. So that's a big חידוש,
chiddush, not just with lashes, even without lashes you can throw him
in on the third time. ואבא שאול אומר אף בשלישית מתרין בו.
veAbba Shaul omer af bashlishis masrin bo. Even on the third time
you only warn him, even if it won't, in the end it
doesn't translate into lashes. ברביעית כונסין אותו לכיפה. berevi'is konsin oso lakippa.
The fourth time you throw him into the כיפה. kippa. והתם מלקות
ליכא במאי קמיפלגי? vehasam malkus leika bemai kamiflegi? And there, there is
no מלקות, malkus, right? So what are they debating about? How do
you explain that? How do you explain why, okay, once we accept
the חידוש chiddush of that teaching that you don't even need to
give him מלקות, malkus, it's just that you know that he was
מזיד meizid and he did it multiple times, which makes sense. Okay,
so you don't need him to defy מלקות, malkus, you don't need
the מלקות. malkus. Once we accept that חידוש, chiddush, what is the
position of אבא שאול Abba Shaul that says you have to wait
till the fourth time? By the third time he did the עבירה
aveira three times, you should throw him into the כיפה kippa by
the third time. Why would you have to wait for the fourth?
מלקות malkus is not relevant. Very good question. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבינא, Ravina, says רבינא, בכיפה צריכה התראה קמיפלגי. bekippa tzericha
hatra'ah kamiflegi. There's a debate whether you have to give the person
warning that you're going if he does this you're going to throw
him into the כיפה. kippa. Okay, so what does that mean? So
everybody holds you need three times. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds
he did it three times, you don't need to warn him you're
going to throw him into the כיפה, kippa, you told him don't
do this sin and therefore you throw him in at the third
time. He's established the pattern. Everybody holds like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
three times. אבא שאול Abba Shaul says no, you need to warn
him that you're going to throw him into the כיפה. kippa. So
he does it three times... Okay, and אבא שאול Abba Shaul also
holds you cannot warn him about the כיפה kipa until he's demonstrated
himself to be a habitual violator. Not exactly clear why that's true.
תוספות Tosafot asks that question, but that's what he says. So he
only after he did it three times is he a habitual violator.
And then before he does it the fourth time, you warn him
if you do this we're going to throw you into the כיפה.
kipa. But if you warned him that time in the third in
this third time, it wouldn't work. You have to warn him about
מלקות malkus and he has to go ahead and do it anyway.
And that's why you need four times according to אבא שאול. Abba
Shaul.
ומאי כיפה? Umai kipa? Now what is this כיפה? kipa? How do
we like physically? אמר רב יהודה מלא קומתו. Amar Rav Yehuda malei
komaso. It was something that was just as high as he was,
a box that was just as high as he was, like solitary
confinement. Not clear also if it was just big enough also, did
he have any room to move around? It doesn't sound like that.
והיכא רמיזא, Veheika remiza, where do we get this idea that we
have the right to do this, and explains he's חייב כרת, chayav
kares, but like where's some hint that we're entitled to do this?
והיכא רמיזא, Veheika remiza, אמר ריש לקיש תמותת רשע רעה,
Amar Reish Lakish timosis
rasha ra'ah, a wicked person, his evil will cause, will bring about
his death. So again, understanding that this is a form of bringing
about his death, this shows us that you know that we can
arrange things, so this is the way it happens. ואמר ריש לקיש
מאי דכתיב, Ve'amar Reish Lakish mai deksiv, what's meant by the verse?
כי גם לא ידע האדם את עתו, Ki gam lo yeda ha'adam
es ito, so this is just because it's, you know,
because we just quoted ריש לקיש Reish Lakish quoting another פסוק, pasuk,
you know, that had to do with death, we're quoting a teaching
of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish on a different פסוק pasuk that has
to do with death, not our death. What is meant by the
פסוק? pasuk? כי גם לא ידע האדם את עתו, Ki gam lo
yeda ha'adam es ito, people, humans don't know their time, כדגים שנאחזים
במצודה רעה, kedagim shenechazim bimetzuda ra'ah, like fish that are caught up
in an evil net. מאי מצודה רעה, Mai metzuda ra'ah, what is
the evil net? אמר ריש לקיש חכה, Amar Reish Lakish chika,
it's a fishing hook,
you know, it's a tiny little thing and that can take, pull
in a huge, huge fish. So you know, and we don't know,
maybe the tiniest little thing will bring about our death. A very
cheery ending to that discussion. Okay, so that was about the person
that did it, that did was a repeat offender even though it
was just מלקות. malkus. But מלקות malkus with a חייב כרת chayav
kares as the גמרא Gemara understands it. Let's see the next משנה.
mishna. ההורג נפש שלא בעדים. Ha'horeg nefesh shelo be'eidin. Let's say you
have somebody who's a murderer but there are no witnesses, you can't
really prosecute him in court. The גמרא Gemara will say, then how
do you know he did it? So this is a different case,
מכניסין אותו לכיפה מאכילין אותו לחם צר ומים לחץ. machnisin oso lekipa
ma'achilin oso lechem tzar umayim lachatz. You put him in a כיפה
kipa as well, so this is seems and and you feed him,
you know, small rations of bread and and a food and very
you know minimum amount of bread and food. So I'll just say
you know that the פשט pshat of the משנה, mishna, unlike the
בבלי Bavli reads it that there's all part of bringing about his
death, is that as opposed to the person who's the repeat offender
for מלקות, malkus, where you give him he's allowed to eat as
much as he wants, עד שכרסו מתבקעת, ad shekreiso mispaka'as, until he
can eat his total fill of barley, this person that is a
murderer you give him you know you know very very meager rations.
That's how that's how at least the פשט pshat is in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi understood. But let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara
says. מנא ידינן? Mina yedinan? How do we know that this person
committed murder if there isn't witnesses? So אמר רב בעדות מיוחדת, Amar
Rav be'eidus meyuechedes,
witnesses that saw it but they didn't see it each one saw
from a different angle, they didn't see one another, and we put
all these hard requirements on the type of testimony you need to
get a person executed. So while there were two witnesses it wasn't
in the exact way that was needed to get him executed. ושמואל
אמר שלא בהתראה. UShmuel amar shelo behasra'ah. They saw it but they
didn't warn him and said that if you do this you're going
to you know get put to death. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, now
that if it were not I should say something about it being
a murderer, because actually this is the whole context of discussing murderers,
right? I mean if it were something like, I don't know, somebody
had been מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos without התראה, hasra'ah, we would not
put him in a כיפה. kipa. This is specifically, this is really
about the rabbis talking about outside of the all of the formal
rules of the תורה. Torah. How do you take responsibility for society
and getting rid of people that are actually real real dangers to
society? So even though this person, you know, that's why specifically this
is about a murderer. And again, I assume it means that there
was evidence that it was intentional, it wasn't an accident, but you
don't have the התראה hasra'ah that would allow us to execute him.
רב חסדא אמר אבימי כגון דאיתכחיש בבדיקות ולא איתכחיש בחקירות. Rav Chisda
amar Avimi kigun de'iskachish bivedikos velo iskachish bachakiros.
You know, you got him off on a technicality, the witnesses contradicted
themselves on some minor question which wasn't really germane and central, and
that was enough to allow us not to execute him, but we
still have to deal with the reality that he's a murderer. Okay,
כדתנן מעשה בבן זכאי בעוקצי תאנים. kednan ma'aseh biBen Zakkai bi'uktzai se'inim.
Ben Zakkai asked even about like the exact you know twigs of
the of the figs, trivial things in order to trip up the
witnesses. But if the guy's a murderer we still have to deal
with him. ומאכילין אותו לחם צר ומים
לחץ. Uma'achilin oso lechem
tzar umayim lachatz. So מאי שנא הכא דקתני נותנים לו לחם צר
ומים לחץ,
mai shna hacha dektani
nosnim lo lechem tzar umayim lachatz, why by the murderer does it
say we give him, you know, small rations of bread and
water, ומאי שנא התם דקתני מאכילין אותו שעורים? umai shna hasam dektani
ma'achilin oso se'orim? עד שיקטו מעיו. ad sheyiktan me'av.
No,
no, no, you have to add, put the two together. We start
him on a diet of meager rations of bread and water, a
small amount, and that causes his stomach to shrink, והדר מאכילים אותו
שעורים vehadar machilim oso se'orim and then you give him barley which
then adds water and it causes his stomach to expand like a
cholent, okay, you add the water, עד שכריסו מתבקעת ad shekreiso mitbaka'as
and that causes the stomach literally, not figuratively, to burst open. So
it reads the two combined, right? Certainly since we're reading that the
thing that is the death is this כריסו מתבקעת, kreiso mitbaka'as, his
stomach bursts, then we have to apply that to the murderer as
well. There's no logic that the murderer should be less worse off.
So we combine the two משניות. Mishnayos. Okay, next משנה, Mishnah, now
that we're dealing with so now we're dealing again with people that
aren't exactly חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but we have to sort of
deal with them. So this משנה Mishnah is also a very famous
teaching about the principle of that we're coming to, קנאים פוגעים בו,
kana'im pogim bo, of where people take the law into their own
hands even though the person is not technically חייב מיתה. chayav misa.
Let's take a look.
הגונב את הקסוה, Hagonev es hakasva, somebody who steals the קסוה, kasva,
which the גמרא Gemara will explain means one of the כלי שרת
klei shares of the
Temple's vessels, והמקלל בקוסם, vehamikalel b'kosem, and somebody who curses God with
a קוסם, kosem, with a prognosticator, with a somebody who predicts the
future, again, what does that mean? We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara.
והבא על הארמית, Vehaba al ha'aramis, this is the one that everybody
knows, and a man who has intercourse with a non-Jewish woman, קנאים
פוגעים בו, kana'im pogim bo, zealous people can come and act and
kill them outside of the law. There's no legal recourse, even as
the court doing things like putting somebody in jail, we as the
court will not deal with these cases in a legal or extra-legal
way, but if somebody wants to act in a vigilante way then
they have the right to, which is fascinating. We will talk about
this. כהן ששימש בטומאה אין אחיו הכהנים מביאים אותו לבית דין, Kohen
sheshimash b'tumah ein achav hakohanim mevi'im oso l'veiss din, here's another case,
if a כהן Kohen does the עבודה avodah and he's טמא, tamei,
so his fellow כהנים Kohanim would not bring him to בית דין,
beiss din,
sounds like there is no punishment in בית דין beiss din for
that, maybe or nothing at least certainly not anything deserving of death.
The גמרא Gemara will discuss this. אלא פרחי כהונה מוציאים אותו חוץ
לעזרה, ella pirchei kehunah motzi'im oso chutz l'azarah, but the young כהנים
Kohanim would take him outside of the Temple courtyard ומפציעים את מוחו
בגזירין, umafzi'im es mocho b'gizirin, and they would, you know, crack open
his head, they would kill him basically with logs, from you know,
with these logs of wood that presumably maybe they had a lot
of wood around there for the for the altar. Okay, זר ששימש
במקדש, Zar sheshimash bamigdash, now what is the story about a, well
that was about somebody that is טמא. tamei. What is about somebody
that's a non-כהן Kohen that does service in the בית המקדש? beiss
hamikdash? רבי עקיבא אומר בחנק, Rabbi Akiva omer b'chenek, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says that that is by strangulation, that's actually executed by the
court. וחכמים אומרים בידי שמים, vachachamim omrim bidei shamayim, that's heavenly. Okay,
but it seems to be that that was maybe heavenly and we
would not take it into our own hands for some reason the
טומאה tumah case we take into our own hands, which is fascinating.
Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי קסוה, Mai kasva, what is this קסוה? kasva? אמר
רב יהודה כלי שרת, Amar Rav Yehuda klei shares, it's a
Temple vessel. וכן הוא אומר ואת קסוות הנסך, v'chein hu omer v'es
kasvos hanasech, which is describing a part of the שולחן, shulchan, whether
it is the big boards that go up on the side or
the bars that support the, you know, the bread, anyway that's how
it's understood to be a piece of one of the
Temple vessels.
Okay, והיכא רמיזא, v'heicha remiza, where is there a hint that this
is something that is deserving of death and that people can sort
of take the law in their own hands? ולא יבאו לראות כבלע
את הקדש ומתו, V'lo yavo'u lir'os k'vala es hakodesh v'meisu, they should
not come in to see, this is talking about the לויים Levi'im
when they, you know, cause the holy vessels, the ארון aron and
the שולחן shulchan and the מנורה menorah to be swallowed up, you
know, to be put away in their bags, they should not see
it at that moment and die. Now that shows that there's an
idea so כבלע את הקדש, k'vala es hakodesh, to swallow the holy
thing, is read here meaning to take possession of, to consume, to
take possession of and it says ומתו, v'meisu, you're deserving of death.
So first it's, you know, as רש"י Rashi points out, this is
just a hint, it's not talking about really stealing, I mean that
would be the sin of מעילה, me'ilah, but it's not deserving of
death and even if there is a hint to the idea that
it's deserving of death, where do you get the idea that we
can people take the law into their own hands? I mean we're
going to see that about the בא על הארמית, ba al ha'aramis,
that's the case of פנחס, Pinchas, right, that's at least the model
for that, but how do we know to apply it to these
other types of cases, this idea of קנאים, kana'im, that's those dots
are not connected.
Okay, והמקלל בקוסם, vehamikalel b'kosem, somebody that curses God with a
קוסם. kosem. תני רב יוסף יכה קוסם את קוסמו, Tani Rav Yosef
yakei kosem es kosmo, somebody believes that this קוסם, kosem, this prognosticator
has special powers, רש"י Rashi says... maybe even believes that he's a
type of a god and says, let the קוסם kosem smite the
one who gives him this, you know, or the wisdom to be
a קוסם, kosem, the wisdom to be a prognosticator, meaning let him
curse God or smite God, maybe he's called his קוסם kosem because,
you know, God is the, if he is a קוסם, kosem, then
God is maybe the ultimate קוסם. kosem. Anyway, you're basically calling on
this קוסם kosem to curse God and treating this קוסם kosem as
a type of a god, and that's technically
not מקלל השם, mekallel hashem, which is saying, you know, using God
to curse God and God's name to curse God, but it's getting,
it's close to that. רבנן ותימא רבה בר מרי אמרי, Rabbanan veteima
Rabba bar Mari amri, יכהו קוסם לו ולקונו ולמקנהו. yakehu kosem lo
ulekono ulemaknehu. You know, the
קוסם kosem should smite so-and-so, a certain person, and his God and
the creator. Right, so similar except a different type of a language
and also including that he should smite another person in addition to
God. גמרא Gemara does not bother here explaining what the basis of
it is, the גמרא Gemara later will say, again, because of similarity
to מקלל השם, mekallel hashem, but also no clarity on why that
translates into קנאים פוגעין בו kanaim pogin bo rather than, I don't
know, בית דין beis din acting. You know, here again, it's maybe
this sense of having to protect what is holy, you know, protect
God, protect the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, maybe the whole
idea of בועל ארמית boel arammit is protecting, you know, the holiness
of the Jewish people, but again, that's a very dangerous idea that
could be expanded to so, so many things. So it's interesting, גמרא
Gemara does not connect those dots. Okay, we will pick up here
tomorrow.